<NBSTEREOEEBOOK>
  <VARIABLES numOfScreens="59" editmode="true"/>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>The first time I sailed past North Brother Island  was also the first time I heard about its history, that it was ruins, that Mary Malone (Typhoid Mary) had died there, and that the General Slocum landed there in flames. It was my first sail through the East River and we were more focused on getting through Hell's Gate at the flood under sail. I made a mental note, though, to come back here. The island had a strong gravitational pull. 

A few years later when Benton Bainbridge approached me to take him to North Brother for an art project I jumped at the offer. After researching the island we realized it made more sense to go through channels. On a brisk November day in 2006 we landed at North Brother in a Parks Department boat that we boarded on Roosevelt Island along with a city  forestry team.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="map_map1.jpeg" imageX="696" imageY="423.3"/>
    <FILE>NB_0076_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    The Fire and the Water, this time</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Due to the ruined condition of the  landing site we had go ashore a few at time by kayak. I was immediately overwhelmed by our limited time and yet there was so much to look at and so much to shoot.

These ruins are the original ferry terminal which was near where we had landed.



Though this is a kind of 3D that can be seen by someone with one eye, it is more subtle than more traditional methods of rendering 3D where each image of a stereo pair are delivered to one eye or the other. Sending a left image to the left eye and a right image to the right eye reveals 3D that is deep and the entire field of view is in 3D. 

Wiggle 3D orients the two images of a stereo pair on top of each other where a point in space is converged. The convergent point is motionless or nearly so, and the rest of the image will twist around the convergent point revealing the space around that point. 

The top slider controls the speed of switching between the two images. The slider beneath it will change the convergent point, and in so doing you can explore the space of the photo and how it's rendered. Play around with the two sliders.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="702" imageY="306.25"/>
    <FILE>NB_0079_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>The city built Riverside Hospital on North Brother in 1885 to replace its original quarantine hospital, also called Riverside. The first Riverside Hospital was on Blackwell’s Island, now known as Roosevelt Island. 

Riverside's earliest patients suffered from typhoid, diptheria, smallpox, scarlet fever, tuberculosis, polio and leprosy (6 of the original patients were lepers). They were largely poor and predominantly immigrants: no one who could afford private care would choose to come here.

The ferry brought patients, workers and supplies to the island from 132nd Street in the Bronx, conditions permitting. Riverside Hospital's early years were plagued by food shortages and harsh winters. Robert Martin, a survivor of the island, remarked that “the experience while there can be compared to the Black Hole of Calcutta.”</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="701" imageY="300.25"/>
    <FILE>NB_0033_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>By 1914, most of Riverside's patients were quarantined for tuberculosis or venereal diseases. Riverside functioned as a quarantine hospital for tuberculosis until its closing in 1942. A large tuberculosis pavilion was built on the island in 1941, but the hospital closed before it was ever used.

Riverside was abandoned and then repurposed for GI housing after the passing of the GI Bill after WWII. Veteran college students and their families were transported to and from the island via the E 134th Street Ferry Terminal, by the ferry boats Mott Haven and Greenwich Village. This was North Brother's golden age; the only time its inhabitants were happy to be there.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="north_brother_satellite.jpg" imageX="701" imageY="427.25"/>
    <FILE>NB_0037</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>
      <LEFT>hospital for tuberculosis until its closing in 1942. A large tuberculosis pavilion was built on the island in 1941, but the hospital closed before it was ever used.

Riverside was abandoned and then repurposed for GI housing after the passing of the GI Bill after WWII. Veteran college students and their families were transported to and from the island via the E 134th Street Ferry Terminal, by the ferry boats Mott Haven and Greenwich Village. This was North Brother's golden age; the only time its inhabitants were happy to be there.

Riverside was abandoned and then repurposed for GI housing after the passing of the GI Bill after WWII. Veteran college students and their families were transported to and from the island via the E 134th Street Ferry Terminal, by the ferry boats Mott Haven and Greenwich Village. This was North Brother's golden age; the only time its inhabitants were happy to be there.</LEFT>
      <RIGHT>By 1914, most of Riverside's patients were quarantined for tuberculosis or venereal diseases. Riverside functioned as a quarantine.

A large tuberculosis pavilion was built on the island in 1941, but the hospital closed before it was ever used.

Riverside was abandoned and then repurposed for GI housing after the passing of the GI Bill after WWII. Veteran college students and their families were transported to and from the island via the E 134th Street Ferry Terminal, by the ferry boats Mott Haven and Greenwich Village. This was North Brother's golden age; the only time its inhabitants were happy to be there.

A large tuberculosis pavilion was built on the island in 1941, but the hospital closed before it was ever used.

Riverside was abandoned and then repurposed for GI housing after the passing of the GI Bill after WWII. Veteran college students and their families were transported to and from the island via the E 134th Street Ferry Terminal, by the ferry boats Mott Haven and Greenwich Village. This was North Brother's golden age; the only time its inhabitants were happy to be there.

A large tuberculosis pavilion was built on the island in 1941, but the hospital closed before it was ever used.

Riverside was abandoned and then repurposed for GI housing after the passing of the GI Bill after WWII. Veteran college students and their families were transported to and from the island via the E 134th Street Ferry Terminal, by the ferry boats Mott Haven and Greenwich Village. This was North Brother's golden age; the only time its inhabitants were happy to be there.</RIGHT>
    </NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="north_brother_satellite.jpg" imageX="40" imageY="373.45"/>
    <FILE></FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>North Brother's next incarnation as an adolescent drug treatment center was not nearly so happy. The city opened the rehab in 1952; it was closed by 1963, amid charges of corruption and failure.




Originally I was simply enabling Benton to get to North Brother Island to shoot HD video for a show we eventually performed together at EyeBeam, along with a group of other artists. I had taken along my new digital still camera, an old video camera and my Revere 3D camera. Different sites I shot with different cameras. These photos are from the Revere shooting on Ektachrome slide.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0052_dot_02</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
   <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>
      <LEFT>Starter Text</LEFT>
      <RIGHT>Starter Text</RIGHT>
    </NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE></FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>This is one of the first buildings you see when you arive at the island. It was very decrepit and though we walked through other buildings before this, this building seemed too dangerous to explore the interior.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="540" imageY="485.29999999999995"/>
    <FILE>NB_0053_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>North Brother Island's most famous resident was Mary Mallon, better known as Typhoid Mary.  Mary emigrated to America from Cookstown (no kidding!), Ireland in 1869, at about the age of fifteen.  She was a talented cook, and earned a better living than she would have in another domestic service job.

She was hired to cook for a wealthy New York banker and his family at their rented summer house in Oyster Bay, Long Island in 1906. Six out of eleven people in that house fell ill with typhoid. 

Typhus was not common in Oyster Bay at that time (it was primarily a disease of the poor, who lived in far more unsanitary conditions), and the owners of the house feared they would not be able to rent their property out again. They hired a sanitation engineer named George Soper to find the cause of the outbreak.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="island_seen_from_river.jpeg" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0054</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>George Soper was the first to realize that the typhus-stricken households he was investigating all shared a middle-aged, single, heavy-set Irish cook. She changed jobs frequently, leaving weeks after each outbreak with no forwarding information. Soper's research eventually linked her to twenty two cases of typhoid fever in New York City and Long Island. 

Mary did not suffer from typhus herself; she was healthy and physically robust. She was outraged by Soper's suggestion that she had caused the outbreaks and angrily refused to give him stool and urine samples. Legend has it that she threatened him with a meat cleaver.

The New York City Health Department sent one of their own doctors, Dr. Sara Josephine Baker, to talk to Mary. Again, Mary protested that she had done nothing wrong and that she was being unjustly persecuted. Ultimately, it took Dr. Baker, a few police officers and some prison matrons to get the samples. The samples proved it: Mary's gall bladder was riddled with typhoid bacteria.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0061</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>She was offered a deal: stop working as a cook, or have her gall bladder removed. Surgery at that time was extremely high-risk; she very likely could have died.  She refused to do either, adamantly denying that she was a carrier. She had already admitted to health officials that she saw no reason to wash her hands often while cooking. Faced with her complete refusal to cooperate, the Department of Health sent her to live in an isolated cottage on North Brother Island. 

Health officials claimed that sections 1169 and 1170 of the Greater New York Charter empowered them to quarantine even an apparently healthy woman like Mary Mallon:

    The board of health shall use all reasonable means for ascertaining the existence and cause of disease or peril to life or health, and for averting the same, throughout the city. [Section 1169]

    Said board may remove or cause to be removed to [a] proper place to be by it designated, any person sick with any contagious, pestilential or infectious disease; shall have exclusive charge and control of the hospitals for the treatment of such cases. [Section 1170]

The charter was written before the mechanism of a healthy carrier was understood; technically, Section 1170 did not apply here, as Mary Mallon was not sick.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0064</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Two years into her confinement on North Brother, Mallon sued the city.  For nearly a year before the trial, Mallon sent stool samples to a private lab that determined they were negative for typhoid. 

The city's tests showed different results: 120 of 163 samples tested positive.

Mallon's lawsuit was rooted in her conviction that she had always enjoyed good health and that her own lab results proved it.

    "This contention that I am a perpetual menace in the spread of typhoid germs is not true. My own doctors say I have no typhoid germs. I am an innocent human being. I have committed no crime and I am treated like an outcast -- a criminal. It is unjust, outrageous, uncivilized. It seems incredible that in a Christian community a defenseless woman can be treated in this manner."

The judge found the city's test results more compelling, and Mallon lost her case. The Board of Health of the City of New York ordered her back to the cottage on North Brother Island.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0065</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>In 1910, a new New York State Commissioner of Health, Eugene H. Porter, M.D., changed the quarantine policy concerning carriers that had led to Mallon's removal to North Brother. 

On February 19, 1910, Mallon accepted the deal she had rejected three years earlier. She agreed to stop working as a cook, and to take precautions to avoid spreading disease. She was freed.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0067</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Mallon honored the terms of her release for a while, working as a laundress and in other positions of domestic service. These jobs offered neither the money, the status,  nor the satisfaction of cooking.

In January of 1915, the Sloane Maternity Hospital in Manhattan had a major outbreak of typhoid fever. Twenty-five people were infected; two of them died. 

A recently-hired cook named Mrs. Brown was implicated. She was described as a heavy Irish-American woman and she had vanished when the outbreak began. She was found on a Long Island estate, cooking.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0067a</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Once again, Mary Mallon was confined to her isolated cottage on North Brother Island. During her time on North Brother she worked as a "nurse," a "hospital helper," and in the hospital's lab. 

Throughout her first quarantine, she was perceived as a sympathetic and tragic figure, deprived of her freedom through no fault of her own. The second time around, she was seen as a figure of horror and evil, a willful spreader of death.

It's uncertain exactly how many illnesses and deaths began with Typhoid Mary. At least three deaths and fifty one illnesses are laid at her door, but the numbers could actually be much higher.

She suffered a massive stroke in December of 1932, and she died of pneumonia in 1938. An autopsy showed a liver that was heavily infected with Typhoid bacteria. 

Her remains were cremated, and she was finally allowed off the island to be buried at St. Raymond’s Cemetery in the Bronx.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0068</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES/>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0069</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>The island had it's own power plant which burned coal to generate electricity. This shot is from inside the coal storage building.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0078</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0072</FILE>
  </PAGE>

  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Try adjusting the convergence point on this image.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0001</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0002</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0003</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0004</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0005</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0006</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0007</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0009</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0021_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0022_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0026_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0027</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0029</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0042</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0082</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0083</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0084</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0087</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0088</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0091</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0092</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Typhoid Mary died in a bungalo on North Brother Island in the year of 1856. If only she kept her promise she would have been able to live out her time amoung the healthy inhabitants of Brooklyn.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0055</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0058</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Typhoid Mary died in a bungalo on North Brother Island in the year of 1856. If only she kept her promise she would have been able to live out her time amoung the healthy inhabitants of Brooklyn.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0008</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>Instead of sailing to North Brother Island on the QT we were taken by the plesant folk of the Parks Department of NYC.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0013</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0030_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0038</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0039</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0040_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0041_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0044</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0045</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0047</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0048</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>maybe DELETE</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0049</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0050_dot</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0051</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0094</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0014</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0017</FILE>
  </PAGE>
  
  <PAGE>
    <TITLE>North Brother Island
    A History in 3D</TITLE>
    <NOTES>There was a ringing in my ears from all the noise of our unspoken words. My heart was broken but not the spirit. These bells rang every day for 1000 years and then they went silent.</NOTES>
    <IMAGE file="" imageX="-1" imageY="-1"/>
    <FILE>NB_0019</FILE>
  </PAGE>

</NBSTEREOEEBOOK>